Finding Aid for F. Thomas Juster papers, 1960-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
F. Thomas Juster papers 1960-2007
Juster, F. Thomas
2012116 Aa 2
F. Thomas Juster was a research scientist and professor of economics at the University of Michigan from 1973 to 1996. His work focused on analyzing household savings and wealth and measuring time use in American families. Juster served as director of the Institute for Social Research from 1976 to 1986. His most notable achievement was his role as founding director of the Health and Retirement Study (HRS) and Asset and Health Dynamics Among the Oldest Old (AHEAD).
8.2 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated by the estate of F. Thomas Juster (donor no 10569 ) in 2011
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
F. Thomas Juster was born in Hollis, Long Island, New York on August 17, 1926.[1] He received his B.S. degree in Education from Rutgers University in 1949 and his Ph.D. in Economics from Columbia University in 1956. Juster's earliest professional positions included serving as a senior research analyst at the Central Intelligence Agency from 1951 to 1953 and assistant professor at Amherst College from 1953 to 1959. From 1959 to 1973, he was on the staff of the National Bureau of Economic Research. In 1973, Juster came to the University of Michigan as professor of economics and research scientist with the Institute for Social Research Survey Research Center, positions he held until 1996.[2] He served as director of the Institute for Social Research from 1976 to 1986. In this capacity, he led efforts to preserve social science funding from budget cuts and testified at congressional hearings as to the need for social science surveys and their importance for public policy.[3] Juster retired and was granted emeritus status in 1996. He served as acting director of the Michigan Retirement Research Center from 2001 to 2002.
Juster's work focused on assessing household savings and wealth and the measurement of time use in American families. In 1985, he co-edited, along with Frank Stafford, the book "Time, Goods, and Well-Being," which pioneered the use of time diaries in collecting time use data.[4]
Juster's most notable contribution to the field of social science was his role as founding director of the Health and Retirement Study (HRS) and its companion study, Asset and Health Dynamics Among the Oldest Old (AHEAD). The HRS was commissioned and funded by the National Institute on Aging and surveys over 26,000 participants over the age of 50 every two years.[5] It has been called "the premier study on retirement, pensions, and the interrelationships between health and economic status in the older population."[6] AHEAD focused on identifying and understanding changes in health, financial well-being, and family resources among the population aged 70 years and older.[7]
In addition to his professional work, Juster chaired many committees and often served in consultative and advisory roles, such as his position as senior advisor for the Brookings Panel on Economic Activity from 1970 to 1990. He was a member of numerous professional associations such as the American Statistical Association, International Sociological Association, and National Association of Business Economists and served on the editorial board of publications including The Review of Income and Wealth and Public Opinion Quarterly.[8].viii Juster was a 1993 recipient of the University of Michigan Senior Research Scientist Lectureship Award for "distinguished contributions to the intellectual environment of the University of Michigan and excellence in research."[9]
Juster died July 21, 2010 at the age of 83. He was survived by his wife Marie and children Thomas, Susan, Arnold, and Maria.
--------------------
Notes:
1. "U-M Economist F. Thomas Juster, Former ISR Director, Dies at 83." Institute for Social Research, University of Michigan. http://www.isr.umich.edu/home/news/juster-obit.html (retrieved 18 June 2012).
2. Curriculum Vita, 2001, Box 2.
3. "U-M Economist"
4. "U-M Economist"
5. "About the Health and Retirement Study." The Regents of the University of Michigan. http://hrsonline.isr.umich.edu/ (retrieved 18 June 2012).
6. "U-M Economist"
7. AHEAD Program Description, Box 1.
8. Curriculum Vita, 2001, Box 2.
9. "U-M Economist"
The F. Thomas Juster papers document Juster's contributions to the field of social science, primarily during his time as research scientist and professor of economics at the University of Michigan. Featured prominently in this collection are records of the Health and Retirement Study, for which Juster served as founding director, as well as his numerous writings. The papers are arranged into eight series: Asset and Health Dynamics Among the Oldest Old, Biographical, Correspondence, Health and Retirement Study, Michigan Retirement Research Center, Testimony, Topical, and Writings.
Subjects:
Juster, F. Thomas (Francis Thomas), 1926-; Retirement--United States--Longitudinal studies.; Social sciences--Research.; Social surveys.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Economics.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
- Asset and Health Dynamics Among the Oldest Old
  The Asset and Health Dynamics Among the Oldest Old (AHEAD) series contains a program proposal and description, comparisons to the HRS study and Longitudinal Study of Aging 2, and material from both the Wave 1 and 2 implementations of the survey, which were undertaken in 1994 and 1995, respectively.
  - Asset Corrections in AHEAD 1993, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Comparison of AHEAD and HRS 1996 (Box 1)
  - Distributions for Modules 2 and 9 by Age and Sex 1995 (Box 1)
  - Longitudinal Study of Aging 2 -- AHEAD Comparison 1996 (Box 1)
  - Program Description 1994 (Box 1)
  - Proposal 1994 (Box 1)
  - Wave 1
    - Codebook 1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Master Files 1994, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Wave 2
    - Assets and Income Section 1995 (Box 1)
    - Computer Program 1995 (Box 1)
    - Coversheet Management Issues 1995 (Box 1)
    - Draft Correspondence 1995 (Box 1)
    - Economic Content Modules 1995 (Box 1)
    - Exit Proxy 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Field Procedures 1995 (Box 1)
    - Health and Cognition Modules 1995 (Box 1)
    - Institutional Interview 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Manual 1995 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Module Suggestions 1995 (Box 1)
    - Pretest 1 1995 (Box 1)
    - Pretest 2 1995, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Schedule/Administrative Issues 1995 (Box 1)
- Biographical
  The Biographical series contains Juster's curriculum vita from 2001 and three photographs showing Juster at events, including one group and two candid photographs.
  - Curriculum Vita 2001 (Box 2)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series includes incoming and outgoing correspondence arranged chronologically from 1992-1998 during the early years of the HRS and AHEAD studies. Most of the material comprising this series concerns these studies, although there is also correspondence related to the Institute for Social Research.
  - 1992, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - 1993, 12 folders (Box 2)
  - 1994, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - 1994, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - 1995, 12 folders (Box 3)
  - 1996, 11 folders (Box 3)
  - 1997, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - 1998, 6 folders (Box 3)
- Health and Retirement Study
  The Health and Retirement Study series contains a wide variety of records relating to the planning, implementation, and results of the study, which aimed to gain further insight into retirement, pensions, and the relationship between health and economic status among the elderly. This includes correspondence between those involved in the project, proposals, and papers written about the study. Also included are survey portions and administrative material for the 1992 (Wave 1), 1994 (Wave 2), 1996 (Wave 3), 1998, and 2000 surveys.
  - 1998 Study
    - Content Recommendations 1997 (Box 3)
    - Disability 1997 (Box 3)
    - Endgame Data 1999 (Box 3)
    - Exit Proxy 1998 (Box 3)
    - Pretest 1 1997 (Box 3)
    - Questionnaire 2001, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Recommendations 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Testing 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Timeline and Administrative 1997 (Box 3)
  - 2000 Study
    - Life Insurance 1999 (Box 3)
    - Questionnaire 1999 (Box 3)
  - 2001 Mail Survey (Box 4)
  - Activities Module 1996 (Box 4)
  - Analysis Ideas 1995 (Box 4)
  - Assets and Income Sections 2000-2006, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Bracketing Technology 1994 (Box 4)
  - Budget Information 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Childhood Questions 1997 (Box 4)
  - Early Results Workshop 1993 (Box 4)
  - Economic Measures Working Group 1994 (Box 4)
  - Enhancing the Research and Policy Value of Administrative Linkages in the HRS, undated (Box 4)
  - Exit Questionnaires 1998-2000 (Box 4)
  - Experimental Modules 1997 (Box 4)
  - Family Booklet 1992 (Box 4)
  - Family Structure and Transfers Working Group 1996 (Box 4)
  - Field Progress Reports 1995 (Box 4)
  - Functional Budgets 1992-1994 (Box 4)
  - Health and Demographic Measurement Working Group 1995 (Box 4)
  - History and Overview 2000 (Box 4)
    (From Research Highlights, Issue #7)
  - Imputation Problems 2000 (Box 4)
  - Instrument Modules 2000 (Box 4)
  - Labor Force Working Group 1996 (Box 4)
  - Memorandum of Understanding, Use of Social Security Administration Administrative Records in the Health and Retirement Survey 1993-1996 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous 1993-2006 (Box 4)
  - Module Requests 2002 (Box 4)
  - Module Suggestions 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  - Newsletters 1999-2001 (Box 4)
  - Papers
    - Construction of the Earnings and Benefits File (EBF) for Use with the Health and Retirement Survey, 1996 (Box 4)
      (by Olivia Mitchell, Jan Olson, and Thomas Steinmeier)
    - How Complete are HRS Work Histories?, 2007 (Box 4)
      (by Alan Gustman and Nahid Tabatabai)
    - HRS Wave I Imputation Procedures, undated (Box 4)
      (by Steven Heeringa and Judith H. Connor)
    - Unfolding Brackets for Reducing Item Nonresponse in Economic Surveys, 1995 (Box 4)
      (by Steven G. Heeringa, Daniel H. Hill, and David A. Howell)
  - Planning Process Working Group 1995 (Box 4)
  - Policy Briefs 1995 (Box 4)
  - Presentation, circa 2000 (Box 4)
  - Proposal 1990 (Box 4)
  - Report to Respondents
    - 1992-1996 (Box 4)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 4)
  - Riders 1997 (Box 4)
  - Steering Committee 2001 (Box 4)
  - Study of Health, Retirement, and Aging Brochure, circa 1997 (Box 4)
  - Testing of CATI/CAPI Application 1994 (Box 4)
  - Two-Minute Interview 1997-1998 (Box 4)
  - Volunteer Activity 1997 (Box 4)
  - Wave 1
    - Assets and Income Sections 1992 (Box 4)
    - Item Missing Data Imputation 1993 (Box 4)
    - Modules 1992 (Box 4)
  - Wave 2 (Box 5)
    - Codebook 1994 (Box 5)
    - "Data Out" Problems 1994 (Box 5)
    - Family Structure 1993 (Box 5)
    - Housing 1993 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1993-1994 (Box 5)
    - Project Manual 1994, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Suggestions 1993 (Box 5)
  - Wave 3
    - Assets and Income Section, circa 1996 (Box 5)
    - Content Recommendations 1995-1996 (Box 5)
    - Exit Proxy 1996 (Box 5)
    - Health Insurance 1996 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1996-1997 (Box 5)
    - Modules 1996 (Box 5)
    - Pension Mini-Pretest 1995-1996 (Box 5)
    - Pretest 1 1995 (Box 5)
    - Pretest 2, circa 1995 (Box 5)
    - Pretest 3 1996 (Box 5)
    - Question Objectives, circa 1996 (Box 5)
    - Response Rates 1996-1997 (Box 5)
    - Schedule and Administrative Issues 1996 (Box 5)
    - Work History (Box 5)
    - Years 6-10
      - Competing Renewal 1994 (Box 5)
      - Proposal 1994 (Box 5)
    - Years 11-16
      - Competing Renewal Proposal, circa 1999 (Box 5)
      - Renewal Budget 1998 (Box 5)
- Michigan Retirement Research Center
  The Michigan Retirement Research Center series includes proposals for the Center, progress reports, newsletters, and working papers. The Michigan Retirement Research Center was established to conduct research on the Social Security system, its long-term solvency, and efforts to reform the system. It was founded as one of three multidisciplinary centers comprising the Retirement Research Consortium with funding from the Social Security Administration and is housed at the University of Michigan.
  - Conference Call Notes 2001 (Box 5)
  - Five-Year Proposal 2003 (Box 5)
  - Newsletters 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - Priority Research Memo 2005 (Box 5)
  - Proposals 1999 (Box 5)
  - Quarterly Progress Reports 2000-2002, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Working Papers
    - Alternative Measures of Replacement Rates, 2006 (Box 5)
      (by Michael D. Hurd and Susann Rohwedder)
    - Changes in Consumption and Activities in Retirement, 2005 (Box 5)
    - Consumption and Economic Well-Being at Older Ages: Income-and Consumption-Based Poverty Measures in the HRS, 2006 (Box 5)
    - Correcting Second Home Equity in HRS/AHEAD: The Issues, a Method, and Some Preliminary Results, 2004 (Box 5)
    - The Effect of Unfolding Brackets on the Quality of Wealth Data in HRS, 2005 (Box 5)
    - Enhancing the Quality of Data on Income and Wealth, 2005 (Box 5)
    - Ensuring Time-Series Consistency in Estimates of Income and Wealth, 2002 (Box 6)
    - How do Immigrants Fare in Retirement?, 2007 (Box 6)
      (by Purvi Sevak and Lucie Schmidt)
    - Labor Market Status and Transitions During the Pre-Retirement Years: Learning from International Differences, 2007 (Box 6)
      (by Arie Kapteyn, James P. Smith, and Arthur van Soest)
    - The Retirement-Consumption Puzzle: Anticipated and Actual Declines in Spending at Retirement, 2004 (Box 6)
    - Year 4 Continuation Proposal, 1998, 2 folders (Box 6)
- Testimony
  The Testimony series contains transcripts of Juster's testimony concerning economic issues before Congress and the Michigan legislature, mostly from the 1970s and 1980s.
  - The Economic Impact of General Revenue Sharing 1975 (Box 6)
    (House Subcommittee Hearings on General Revenue Sharing)
  - The Economic and Political Impact of General Revenue Sharing 1975 (Box 6)
    (House Budget Committee Task Force Hearings on General Revenue Sharing)
  - Inflationary Expectations: Some Characteristics and Relation to Behavior 1979 (Box 6)
    (House Budget Committee Task Force on Inflation)
  - Statement from 3rd Annual Meeting on Economic Conditions, Michigan State Senate 1977 (Box 6)
  - Statement to the Joint Economic Committee on Quality of Economic Statistics 1986 (Box 6)
  - Statement Prepared for Democratic Policy Committee, U.S. Senate 1981 (Box 6)
  - Statement Prepared for HUD and Independent Agencies Subcommittee, Committee on Appropriations 1981 (Box 6)
  - Statement Prepared for Labor and Human Resources Subcommittee on Appropriations, House of Representatives 1981 (Box 6)
  - Statement for Special Study on Economic Change of the Joint Economic Committee, U.S. Congress 1974 (Box 6)
  - Statement before the U. S. Senate Committee on the Budget 1979 (Box 6)
  - Stock Prices and Consumer Spending: An Appraisal of the Great Crash 1988 (Box 6)
    (Statement prepared for the Joint Economic Committee's Hearings on the Economic Outlook)
  - Testimony before the Joint Economic Committee 1973 (Box 6)
  - Testimony before the Senate Committee on Banking, Housing, and Urban Affairs 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Testimony Prepared for Hearings of the House Budget Committee 1980 (Box 6)
  - Testimony to Special Study on Economic Change Regarding Inflation and Consumer Behavior 1978 (Box 6)
- Topical
  The Topical series includes an assortment of material arranged by topic. Prominent in this series are records relating to the Institute for Social Research's 50th Anniversary, Juster's participation in a research consortium under the auspices of the National Planning Association and National Science Foundation, and his proposals and grant applications.
  - 1975-1981Time Use Longitudinal Panel Study 1983 (Box 6)
  - 1993-1994 University Senior Research Scientist Lecture Program, 1994 (Box 6)
  - American Economic Association Committee on the Quality of Economic Statistics 1986-1989 (Box 6)
  - Analysis of Retirement Security Issues Using Simulation Models 1981-1982 (Box 6)
  - Behavioral Science Programs Funding 1982 (Box 6)
  - China Disaggregated Data Bank Project 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence on National Issues 1981-1992 (Box 6)
  - Institute for Social Research
    - 1975 Fall Omnibus (Box 6)
    - 50th Anniversary 1997-1998, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1984-1986, 2000s (Box 6)
  - Longitudinal Retirement History Survey 1987 (Box 6)
  - Minority Female Single Parent Program 1986 (Box 6)
  - National Academy of Sciences Panel on a Research Agenda and New Data for an Aging World 1999-2000 (Box 6)
  - National Planning Association/National Science Foundation Consortium
    - Cooperative Research in Goals Accounting: An Overview of a Research Proposal 1977 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence
      - 1973-1975 (Box 6)
      - 1976-1980 (Box 6)
    - General 1976-1980 (Box 6)
    - National Science Foundation Review Panel's Reviews of Goals Accounting Consortium 1980 (Box 6)
    - Renewal Proposal for Continuation of Account 1978 (Box 6)
    - Satisfaction of Human Wants: Resource Uses, Indicators of Accomplishment and Analysis of Alternative Possibilities of Achievement. An Accounting Framework for the Quality of Life 1975 (Box 6)
      (Research Consortium Proposal)
    - University of Michigan Consortium Proposal 1977-1982, 1977 (Box 6)
  - New York Magazine 1976 (Box 6)
  - Proposals/Grant Applications
    - Appendices to a Proposal to the National Science Foundation for Support of a 1984-1985 Study of Time Allocation Among American Householders, 1983 (Box 6)
    - A Continuation Proposal on a National Survey of the Impact of General Revenue Sharing on State and Local Government 1975 (Box 6)
    - Economic and Psychological Costs and Benefits of Work 1975 (Box 6)
    - Establishment of an Experimental Household Survey Panel Oriented to Public to Policy Issues 1973 (Box 6)
    - Experimental Household Survey Panel Oriented to Public to Policy Issues 1973, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Influence of Family and School Environments on the Cognitive and Social Development of Young Children 1986-1987 (Box 7)
      (A Proposal to the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development)
    - Integrating the Household Sector into a System of National Goals Accounting 1975 (Box 7)
    - A Longitudinal Study of the Relation between School Outputs and Schooling Inputs 1974 (Box 7)
    - The Measurement and Modeling of Household Consumption and Saving Behavior: An Experimental Approach 1974 (Box 7)
    - Private Sector Development 1984 (Box 7)
    - A Proposal to Evaluate the Effects of Federal Revenue Sharing 1974 (Box 7)
    - A Proposal for an Experimental Labor Supply Module on the PSID 1996 (Box 7)
    - Time Use Microdata and Analysis of Unemployment, Income Supplements, and Job Search 1975 (Box 7)
    - Wealth, Savings, and Financial Security Among Older Households 1995 (Box 7)
  - Social Science Funding Issues 1995 (Box 7)
  - Speeches
    - Economic Indicators and the Current Business Situation 1970 (Box 7)
      (Talk before the New York Security Analysts)
  - Survey of Consumer Attitudes Committee 1998-1999 (Box 7)
  - Working Group on Social Knowledge-Producing Institutions 1985 (Box 7)
- Writings
  The Writings series includes a largely complete collection of Juster's published writings, for academic journals and conferences, as well as Institute for Social Research working papers. The writings are arranged alphabetically.
  - General
    - The 1989 Survey of Consumer Finances: A Survey Design for Wealth Estimation, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Access to Research Data: Opportunities, Responsibilities, and Costs 1986 (Box 7)
    - Agenda for Future Research: The Measurement of Social and Economic Performance 1970 (Box 7)
    - The Allocation of Time: Empirical Findings, Behavioral Models, and Problems of Measurement 1991 (Box 7)
    - Alternatives to GNP as a Measure of Economic Progress 1976 (Box 7)
    - An Analysis of Ex-Ante Savings Data: Some Preliminary Results 1971 (Box 7)
    - Anticipations of Purchases of Consumer Durables 1968 (Box 7)
    - Anticipatory and Objective Models of Durable Goods Demand 1970-1972 (Box 7)
    - Article on Health and Retirement Survey in The Encyclopedia of Aging, 1994-1995 (Box 7)
    - Article on Income for Encyclopedia of Economics, 1979 (Box 7)
    - An Assessment of Alternative Measures of Time Use 2003 (Box 7)
    - Asset Corrections in AHEAD 1993, 2005 (Box 7)
    - Basic Research, Productivity, and the Federal Budget 1981 (Box 7)
    - Bubbles in the Melting Pot: Ethnicity, Stereotyping and Discrimination 1978 (Box 7)
    - Categories of Wants and the Indicators of their Achievement for Use in Goals Accounting Research on Quality of Life 1976 (Box 7)
    - Changes over the Decades in Time Spent at Work and Leisure: An Assessment of Conflicting Evidence 1992 (Box 7)
    - Changes in Wealth in the U.S. over the Past Decade 1992 (Box 7)
    - Changes in Work, Leisure, and Well-Being for Men and Women 1985 (Box 7)
    - Changing Times of American Youth: Now and Looking Back Twenty Years 2004 (Box 7)
    - Comments on "The Concept and Measurement of Product Quality 1976 (Box 7)
    - Comments on "The Federal Statistical System's Response to Emerging Data Needs" by Jack E. Triplett 1990-1991 (Box 7)
    - Conceptualizing and Measuring the Generation and Distribution of Well-Being, World Congress of Sociology, Mexico City 1982 (Box 7)
    - Consumer Anticipations Surveys: A Summary of U.S, Postwar Experience 1969 (Box 7)
    - Consumer Awareness of Interest Rates 1974 (Box 7)
    - Consumer Buying Intentions and Purchase Probability: An Experiment in Survey Design 1965 (Box 7)
    - Consumer Sensitivity to Finance Rates: An Empirical and Analytical Investigation 1963 (Box 7)
    - Consumer Sensitivity to the Price of Credit 1964 (Box 7)
    - Consumer Spending Prospects 1979 (Box 7)
    - Consumer Spending Prospects for 1985, 1984 (Box 7)
    - Consumer Spending and Psychology 1987 (Box 7)
    - The Consumption Outlook for 1975 (Box 7)
    - The Consumption Outlook for 1976, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Consumption Prospects, circa 1978 (Box 7)
    - Correcting Second Home Equity in HRS/AHEAD: The Issues, a Method, and some Preliminary Results 2004 (Box 7)
    - Dealing with Inflation: Price Alternatives 1980 (Box 7)
    - The Decline in Household Saving and the Wealth Effect 2004 (Box 7)
    - Differences in the Measurement of Wealth, Wealth Inequality and Wealth Composition Obtained from the Alternative U.S. Wealth Surveys 1990 (Box 7)
    - The Digital Divide Among Children: Closing or Widening at the Turn of the Decade? 2004 (Box 7)
    - The Distribution of Economic Well-Being Introduction, 1977 (Box 7)
    - The Distribution of Wealth in the U.S. Economy: Part 1 undated (Box 7)
    - The Distribution of Well-Being Among Households 1985 (Box 7)
    - The Economy and Consumer Spending 1973 (Box 7)
    - Economic Microdatabases 2000 (Box 7)
    - The Economics and Politics of the Supply-Side View 1987 (Box 7)
    - Economic Psychology: Evaluation and Prospects 1981 (Box 7)
    - Education, Income, and Human Behavior: Introduction and Summary undated (Box 7)
    - Enhancing the Quality of Data on Income: Recent Innovations from the HRS 2001 (Box 7)
    - Enhancing the Quality of Data on Income and Wealth undated (Box 7)
    - Enhancing the Quality of Data on Income: Recent Developments in Survey Methodology 1999 (Box 7)
    - Enhancing the Quality of Data on Income and Wealth: Recent Developments in Survey Methodology 1998 (Box 7)
    - Enhancing Data Quality Through Longitudinal Imputations: Studies of the Income and Asset Data from HRS and AHEAD undated (Box 7)